rights.
Protected layout design。
rights and protected plant variety rights.
Acting President, the Bills Committee supports the bill in principle.
辯論終止待續，條例草案交由內務委員會處理。
在議程的討論中，法案委員會考慮了，當中其他議題。
and enhance its status as a premier intellectual property trading hub in Asia.
and are protected in Hong Kong under the respective dedicated legislations on intellectual properties.
The rationale for choosing the three additional categories of IBRs for inclusion in the proposed profits tax deduction.
the deeming provisions in respect of the trading receipts of IPRs and relevant anti-avoidance measures.
Acting President, as Chairman of the Bills Committee on Income Revenue Amendment No.2 Bill 2018, I now give a brief account of the work of the Bills Committee.
The impact on tax revenue, the mechanism for determining the true market value of IPRs for tax assessment.
As advised by the administration, the three additional categories of IPRs are covered by the World Trade Organisation agreement on trade-related aspects of intellectual property rights.
本會恢復二零一八年税務修訂第二號條例草案嘅二讀辯論。條例草案委員會主席梁繼昌議員先就委員會報告向本會發言。梁繼昌議員。
The objective of the bill is to amend the inland revenue ordinance to expand the scope of the existing profits tax deduction for capital expenditure incurred for the purchase of intellectual property rights to cover three additional categories of IPRs, namely performers, econ
According to the administration, the legislative exercise is to give effect to the proposal as announced by the financial secretary in the 2016-17 budget, and will bring about positive effects to the development of the intellectual property industry in Hong Kong.
在確定真值的購併成本的相關IPRs。
IRD將 make reference to the arm's length principle and determine real taxable profits.
包括的併購成本， incurred for the three additional categories of IPRs。
The Inland Revenue Department also does not have relevant data for estimation because capital expenditure.
is not tax deductible at present, and therefore no relevant claim has been recorded.
for an assignment of or an agreement to assign a performer's right in relation to a performance given by the performer in Hong Kong.
會被 deem 作為應課税收入，產生於或 derive 來自於香港進行的貿易、職業或業務。
the bills committee is concerned that an enterprise may overclaim the amount of capital expenditure incurred for the purchase of IPRs for tax deduction.
The Bills Committee notes that proposed Section 151B B under Clause 3 of the Bill provides that sums received by or accrued to a performer or an organiser.
行政已經有建議，指出，由於市場資訊有限，以及缺乏有關交易量的統計數據，因此，目前尚無法精確估算。
And has sought details of the mechanism for determining whether an alleged purchase cost of an IPR in a transaction is eligible for deduction under the regime of profits tax deduction.
The inclusion of the three additional categories of IPRs will render the scope of profit tax deduction in respect of capital expenditure incurred for the purchase of IPRs under the ordinance more comprehensive.
On members' inquiry about the impact of the legislative proposal on government's tax revenue, in particular the estimated amount of tax revenue to be foregone pursuant to the proposed profits tax deduction.
行政已經確保成員們，IRD有個已建立的機制，來防範 abuses，當一個税項減免申請不代表該IPR在購買或出售時的真實市場價值。
For transactions involving related parties,IRD would take into account relevant transfer pricing provisions and consider whether the anti-avoidance provisions of the ordinance will be applicable should the relevant cases demonstrate an intent of tax avoidance or tax evasion.
the bills committee however notes that the total amount of deduction claimed in respect of capital expenditure on the purchase of the existing five categories of tax deductible IPRs for the year of assessment 2015 to 16 was 846 million dollars.
和税，所charged。
Members noted that term in clause 3, 1 and 2.
Where section 20B of the ordinance applies, the non-resident person concerned.
shall be recoverable by all means under the ordinance from that person in Hong Kong.
The Bills Committee has also examined the meaning and scope of the term performers' right under Clause 3 of the Bill.
The administration has explained that the said proposed section is applicable to both Hong Kong residents and non-residents.
As performers economic rights are transmissible, whereas performers non-economic rights are not assignable or transmissible.
In case non-residents are involved, I.R.D. has an established mechanism for tax assessment and collection.
Clause seven of the bill proposes to extend the above arrangement to sums deemed to be trading receipts under proposed section 51BB.
That person in Hong Kong shall, at the time he makes the payment, deduct from those sums which are sufficient to produce the amount of such tax.
It is necessary for clause 3.1 and 2 of the bill to cover both types of the rights, so as to clarify what sums received or
includes both performers' economic rights and non-economic rights, whereas the same term in Clause 3.3 practically covers performers' economic rights only.
The administration has explained that the term performance right includes both economic rights which are assignable and non-economic rights which are not assignable.
將被課税， in respect of the sums concerned in the name of any person in Hong Kong who has paid those sums to that or another non-resident person.
The administration has been requested to clarify whether and how the use of the same term, performers' right, could be able to reflect the administration's different policy intent under the said provisions.
the bills committee has inquired howIRD will conduct tax assessment and tax collection in respect of a non-resident person who is chargeable to tax in respect of sums deemed by the said proposed section to be trading receipts arising in or derived from Hong Kong.
喺香港。
the bills committee has inquired.
arising from the assignment rather than mere use of performance rights.
In bracket 4b of the ordinance, should be reviewed or removed.
of IPRs， to the effect that tax deduction is not allowable under certain circumstances.
yet the administration has not taken up such proposal on the ground that the proposal.
since only economic rights are assignable, clause three three of the bill will practically cover economic rights only.
行政已經指出，Taking the words in context，the reference to performers in the relevant provision is clear enough.
may be regarded as encouraging the manufacturers' transfer of company profits via transfer pricing arrangements.
The administration has explained that Section 16EC4B was introduced in 2001 as an anti-avoidance provision.
Received by or accrued to a person for the use of performers' right should be deemed as trading receipts arising in or derived from Hong Kong.
referring to the view expressed by some deputations that the restrictions under the existing section 16 EC.
whether the administration would change its stance in respect of the review of sections 39E and 16EC of the ordinance.
in this regard, trading receipts can arise from the use of both economic rights and non-economic rights. Clause 33 of the bill, however, seeks to deal with some received.
Class six of the bill seeks to amend section sixteen EC of the ordinance to provide that the existing anti-avoidance measures in relation to tax deduction for capital expenditure for the purchase of the existing five categories of IPRs would also apply to the three additional categories.
the bills committee notes that the industrial sector has been appealing to the administration over the years to amend section 39e and 16c of the ordinance to enable manufacturers to claim tax allowances in respect of the machinery equipment and IPRs used in the production procedures located outside.
和相關的委員會在研究。
但係，也係税安排喺內地。
的委員會同意行政的修訂。
同埋，優化税務措施去刺激。
The administration will take into account the views expressed by members.
On the issues relating to Section 39E and 16EC.
Following similar principles behind Section 39E of the ordinance.
誒期間亦都有十一份嘅書面意見書，係集合咗業界同埋團體嘅有關意見。
科研同埋創新科技嘅一連串嘅誒政策嘅行動。
行政已經有明確的建議，指出這個議題不僅涉及香港的税制政策。
在光大可能經濟整合，那可能被帶來由發展的廣東、香港、澳門灣區。
The following part of the speech carries my personal view on the bill。啊，主席，啊，今次嘅條例草案咧，其實係舉行咗兩次會議。
而呢一個嘅誒税務條例修訂草案，可以係講話係一連串誒特區政府為咗鼓勵。
The administration has communicated with industry and is re-examining the issues and will study and explore feasible options that comply with the principles of tax symmetry and transfer pricing.
Acting President, the Bills Committee notes that the administration has proposed a textual amendment to the Chinese text of a provision under Clause 5(2) of the Bill, so as to align it with the English text.
The purpose of Section 19EC 4B is to deny tax deduction for IPRs which are used outside Hong Kong by a party other than the taxpayer for production of profits not chargeable tax in Hong Kong.
資本性嘅支出係一個扣税，咁喺。
受保護嘅布圖設計。
無辦人嘅香港嘅營業嘅收入。
同埋受保護嘅啊植物品種。
即係其實喺啲集成嘅電路板，即係topography。
嘅啊反避税嘅原則咧，先至可以扣除嘅。
縱使佢係一個資本帳項都好咧，係可以扣税嘅。
個嘅誒現有嘅税務條例嘅條款底下咧，呢一啲嘅知識產權咧，其實咧係可以。
咁另外咧，我哋要注意到咧喺草案嘅第三條第三款入邊咧，其實亦都有一個新增嘅反避税建議，就係關於呢個轉讓表演者嘅經濟啊權嗰個收入咧。
嗱，其實嗰個條例草案係好簡單，只係將啊知識產權嘅定義係加咗啊三個新嘅類別，分別咧即係由五個類別咧係增加到現時嘅八個類別。呢三個類別咧分別係表演者嘅經濟利益權啦。
而總的嚟講咧，加入呢三種新嘅知識產權嘅類別咧，係會令到購買呢一啲知識產權嘅開支嗱，呢啲原本咧係一啲資本嘅開支，一般嘅啊資本開支，主席啊代主席，你係會計師都知道係不可能扣税嘅，就因為呢一。
嗱，其實呢一個條例草案亦都有一啲好基本，亦都並不是過於嚴緊嘅一啲啊反避税嘅誒誒條款喺度。而當然啦，啊呢三類型嘅新嘅啊知識產權嘅類別咧，都要合乎翻呢啲最基本嘅。
本來都係一個啊資本性嘅收入啊，資本性收入咧喺税例現現有香港税例底下咧，係唔會喺正常情況底下係唔會當作係一個營業嘅收入。但係因為咧喺呢度咧，我哋係畀咗呢一個嘅啊。
基於呢個税務相稱嘅原則底下咧，喺呢一度嚟講，如果係有一個啊表演者或者一個籌辦人咧，如果係因為轉讓呢個表演表演者嘅經濟收入而係收到一個款項咧，嗱呢一個咧係會視為該啊表演者或者籌。
而亦都有啊，草案委員會嘅啊委員問到税局：喂，究竟呢一個嘅啊加多三項嘅啊扣減，究竟係對於我哋嘅税收有幾大嘅影響嗱？當然啊，代主席，你喺我嘅剛。
剛才嘅啊英文嘅匯報嗰度底下，你都聽到咧，係税局係未能夠誒有一個好整全嘅數字嘅，但係可以話翻畀大家聽咧。喺二零一五至一六年度嘅課税年度咧，啊現時嗰五類嘅啊五類嘅啊知識產權。
多謝主席。
提交上嚟。
都會有嘅。
黃定光議員。
審議草案工作咧，每年。
而本條例草案咧，亦都係同税務有關嘅。
不足為奇，但係今年咧特別多有關税務嘅修訂條例草案條文。
呢啲草案對業界嚟講咧，都係有助減輕有關佢哋嘅資本開支嘅。
可為有益無害，所以咧，我同埋民建聯咧都會表示支持嘅。
我咧差唔多每條同税務相關嘅條例草案都有份參與審議工作，甚至係擔任委員會嘅主席。
啊！主席，我喺度僅次發言係支持呢條條例嘅二讀，亦都希望各位誒議會嘅同事係支持呢條條例草案嘅二讀同埋三讀。唔該。
就係將購買知識產權所招致嘅資本開支咧嘅利得扣税範圍咧，係由現時嘅五類擴展到八類。
而新增呢三類咧，分別係表演者嘅經濟力權益權利、受保護嘅布圖設計即係拓樸圖嘅權利，同埋受保護植物品種嘅權利。
後嘅啊一年或者兩年時間咧，可以喺相關嘅啊事務委員會咧，係對我哋嘅議員去作出一個回報，究竟呢一啲嘅啊寬免措施係為香港帶嚟幾多嘅經濟效益？
喺利得税扣減方面咧，係總共係啊，消費咗、消耗咗係八點四六億嘅港元。當然啦，我哋不能夠咧係淨係睇睇究竟我哋係啊喺個支出度係少收咗幾多税款，亦都應該睇睇考慮翻究竟由於呢一個。
個嘅資本性扣減呢個咁特別嘅優惠咧，係令到香港作為一個啊知識產權嘅註冊中心，係帶嚟咗幾多嘅經濟效益。而我都好希望啊政府能夠喺呢條條例草案啊通過咗、實施咗之後。
提。
咁去説明嘅。
政府應當係積極進行。
呢啲都可以發揮咗積極嘅作用。
但係，我關注到，由於唔少中小企。
另外一方面，扣税嘅建議得到大多數人嘅支持。
對政府而言，擴闊有關扣税範圍嘅目的。
故此啊，若果要講推動香港知識產權業嘅發展咧，
都唔知點解要拖到三年到今日先有進一步擴闊呢個去實行啊！
對保護知識產權嘅意識仍然唔夠高，警惕性咧係需要有所改進提高嘅。
除咗委員會之外咧，亦接到不同嘅團體意見書，裡面咧都均表贊成嘅。
我亦都關注到喺申請扣税嘅時候咧，未有真實咁反映咗購買或者出售之產權市場價值嘅問題。
對於涉及原有五個同埋新增三個類別有關扣税制度安排咧，佢哋都未必能夠完全瞭解。
就係為咗推動香港成為區內知識產權貿易中心，對香港知識產權業嘅發展，以及提升本港喺亞洲知識產權貿易中心嘅地位。
然而，新增嘅三類知識產權提供嘅法定保護，其實早已經實施咗一段時間嘅啦。而且為購買知識產權擴闊嘅扣税範圍咧，係知識產權保護工作小組早喺二零一五年三月提出嘅建
所以，我哋喺審議條例草案期間咧，我都提出相關扣税嘅原則、定義同埋操作呢啲問題咧。尤其是係表演者嘅經濟權誒權利同埋受保護植物品種權利方面咧，需要由局方咧係清楚。
如果有。
而涉及關聯嘅。
所以，我認為喺立法之後啊。
畀企業研究、研發、創新。
需要清晰咁講清楚，同埋去理解。
而決定取得某項積產權開支嘅真正價值。
關乎呢啲問題啊，喺中小企方面咧，同樣會遇到嘅。
關聯方嘅交易咧，税局會考慮相關轉讓定價條款。
相信有助鼓勵企業研究使用同埋購買更多嘅知識產權。
特區政府有關當局咧，係有需要加強向業界作出詳盡嘅介紹。
並且要加強宣傳嘅工作，亦需要咧更密切溝通聯繫，解答疑問。
即係指某項交易嘅交易雙方之間，即使沒入冇關聯咧，有關嘅定價咧，亦應該相同嘅。
對此咧，當局有乜嘢可以防範嘅機制以杜絕呢啲情況咧？當局回應指，税務局會根據獨立交易嘅原則。
期望當積產權貿易喺企業之間發展成熟咧，係有助企業轉型咧，邁向自主研發同埋建立品牌嘅。
有關嘅個案顯示有避税或者逃税嘅意圖咧，就會考慮誒用税務條例下低反避税條例誒，會唔會適用啦？
業界認為到而家呢個社會營商環境之中啊，係通滿充滿咗挑戰。中小企咧係面對嘅問題更加係好多。擴闊税務嘅優惠範圍咧，的確係有助創造有利嘅環境咧。
啊，主席。
有冇其他議員想發言？
已喺二零一七年係向立法會提交條例草案㗎。
如果冇，我現在請商務及經濟發展局局長答辯，之後辯論即告結束，局長。
噉就住剛才黃定光議員所講嘅，要加強對業界嘅宣傳同埋推廣呢方面，我哋係十分之同意嘅。
條例草案如果係獲得通過，就購買知識產權嘅資本開支所提供嘅扣税安排，將會涵蓋各項主要類別嘅知識產權。
上述擴闊扣税範圍嘅建議啦，係有助鼓勵企業參與發展知識產權嘅商業活動，從而啦進一步擴誒鞏固香港作為區內知識產權貿易中心嘅地位。
二零一八年税務修訂第二號條例草案喺今年四月提交立法會審議，我非常之感謝法案委員會主席梁繼昌議員同埋其他委員嘅努力同埋全力支持，令到審議工作係順利完成。
喺法案委員會審議階段啦，條例草案得到委員嘅普遍支持。此外啦，全部十一個曾經向法案委員會提交書面意見嘅團體，亦都係表示支持條例草案提出嘅建議㗎。
事實上，為咗支援啊企業，包括剛才啊黃議員所講嘅中小企啦，去創造同埋使用知識產權，政府啦其實我哋係推出咗一係列嘅措施，包括提供免費嘅初步知識產權諮詢服務。
嘅扣減條例草案建議將扣税範圍由上述五類嘅知識產權增至八類，新增嘅三類知識產權係集成電路嘅布圖設計、拓撲圖、植物品種同埋表演嘅權利。
協助中小企更加認識知識產權同埋制定有效嘅知識產權管理同埋商品化嘅策略，以及咧推出知識產權管理人員計劃，支援中小企業建立知識產權人力資源，協助中小企管理知識產權以及進行知識產權商品化等等嘅措施㗎。
主席，有關知識產權嘅政策能夠與時並進，當然係一件好事。同時咧，係得到支持，發展應該更加多加加大力度去推動。主席，本人僅止陳辭，支持本條例草案同埋佢嘅修訂案。
正如我哋動議二讀嗰陣時表示，條例草案旨在擴闊購買知識產權嘅資本開支嘅利得税扣税範圍。而家企業購買專利權、工業知識、版權、註冊外觀設計同埋註冊商標呢五類知識產權嘅資本開支，可以根據税務條例獲得利得税。
咁另外就住黃議員剛才所講嘅啊，點解個時間會咁長啦？咁其實政府喺二零一六年至一七嘅財政預算案公佈有關措施啦之後啦，隨即係展開咗各項準備嘅工作㗎。並且喺二零一六年十一月啦，係徵詢立法會工商事務委員會嘅意見，原意。
條例草案獲得通過之後啦，税務扣減啦係會由二零一八一九嘅課税年度嘅評税機期起生效。換言之啦，只要任何公司喺評税機期喺二零一八年四月一號或者之後完結啦，喺呢個評税機期開始購買三種新。
反對嘅請舉手。
增指明知識產權嘅資本開支都可以獲得扣税㗎。
本會現在成為全體委員會審議二零一八年。
知識產權類別實施財政預算案嘅建議，惠及業界，推動香港發展成為區內嘅知識產權貿易中心。我僅此陳辭，多謝。
我現在向各位提出嘅待決議題係二零一八年税務修訂第二號條例草案，予以二讀，贊成嘅請舉手。
我認為議題獲得在席議員以過半數贊成，我宣佈議案獲得通過。二零一八年税務修訂第二號條例草案。
咁稍後啦，我會喺全體委員會啦嘅階段啦，動議一項簡單嘅修正案，將條例草案第五括弧二條中文文本中「布圖設計」、「拓樸圖權利」一詞啦，係修訂為「布圖設計」。
令到有關表述同該條文嘅英文文本啦，更加係對應㗎。法案委員會係支持呢個項誒依項嘅修訂案嘅。噉我懇請各位議員支持條例草案，以及我哋將喺全體委員會階段提出嘅修正案，令到我哋能夠早日擴闊有關扣税安排適用嘅。